<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Is not the hand of Joab in all this? Or an enquiry into the grounds of a late pamphlet intituled, the mystery of the new-fashioned-goldsmiths, or bankers, &amp;c. and answering the exceptions in it to the bankers trade.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45789</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831910</idno>
  <idno type="VID">36377</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240936246</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220511</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831910</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831910e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1779:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Is not the hand of Joab in all this? Or an enquiry into the grounds of a late pamphlet intituled, the mystery of the new-fashioned-goldsmiths, or bankers, &amp;c. and answering the exceptions in it to the bankers trade.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The mystery of the new fashioned goldsmiths.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Banks and banking --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Bankers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36377:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Is not the Hand of</hi> JOAB <hi>in all this?</hi> OR An Enquiry into the Grounds of a late Pamphlet Intituled, THE MYSTERY OF THE New-fashioned-Goldsmiths, OR BANKERS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> AND Answering the EXCEPTIONS in it to the <hi>Bankers Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36377:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36377:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Enquiry into the Grounds of a late</hi> PAMPHLET <hi>Entituled,</hi> THE MYSTERY OF THE New-fashioned Goldsmiths, or Bankers, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving lately seen a Pamphlet under the Title of <hi>The My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of the New-fashioned Goldsmiths or Bankers,</hi> &amp;c. I presently conjectured what I found it to be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; A prosecution of the design managed of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te by so many clandestine whisperings of Jealousie into the Ears of unwary People, and the spreading of false and scandalous Reports, to bring that Breach upon the Credit of this famous City, (and by consequence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Kingdom) which so many of all degrees and professions have already felt no little of the evil of: The restless Spirit of this Author thinking scorn to reflect upon the most convincing guilt cast upon him by the many Ruines which his past Artifices have wrought, but as if he made it a sport to do mischief, pursues his project by a new device. Thus he endeavours by this pretended Letter to confirm those surmises with a shew of Reason, which he first attempted by rumor and surprize upon the minds of the People; well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36377:3"/>that false and foolish arguings are then most like to bear a better appearance to them, when by fraud and practise their fears and jealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies are alarm'd, and (by the venomous effect thereof) they stand confounded and prejudiced in their understandings and judgments.</p>
            <p>I marveled at first, comparing the Title (where we have the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor taking upon him the Name of a Merchant) with the Letter, (where I find his opinion so cross to the sentiments of all other of that Profession) what kind of Trader this should be; especially while I find him so much at leisure, as upon so slender a Theam to trace the series of above thirty years, with such abundant industry, concerning the Rise, Growth, State and Decay of the <hi>Bankers:</hi> But my Genius soon satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied me in this point, well remembring that there are some <hi>New-fashioned Traders,</hi> whom I forbear to define further, who under pretence thereof walk the Exchange as very Merchan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, that have both time enough to busie themselves about other mens matters, and their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures being rather the diversion of their fancies than their business, and way of subsistance, know little, and perhaps care less, what the true Circumstances of a Merchant are with reference to the <hi>Banker:</hi> and yet (forsooth) presuming under the notion of an observing Merchant, to determine a matter of so much moment to the Interest of the Trade of the whole Kingdome, as no one thing besides it could be. But the matter having a Mystery in it (as he further tells us in his Title) he should have handled it with a little more modesty than he doth, few that attempt to open Mysteries, expounding them so right, but leave just occasion for other men to dissent from their judgments, and oft times to correct their Errors. But enough of the Title, now to the Letter.</p>
            <p>Wherein it being plain that it is the main business of our Author to dissemble his true end in the penning and publishing of it, and yet so to calculate and put it together, as to make the whole drive at the end he designs, it will be requisite to inquire into his end, <hi>What it is,</hi> and shew, that the pretendeded occasion of this Letter was not the intent of his writing it; Towards which it is to be observed,</p>
            <p>That it would reflect too much imputation of Levity upon a thirty years observer and discoverer of Mysteries to tell such a long and studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Story to a Country Gentleman, upon the single occasion of his Sons disposal to a Trade, it being of all things most ridiculous in a man that would be had in reputation for wisdom, to shew himself disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his Discourses, to the nature of the subject whereof he treats. Nor will I so far prejudge his Charity to the <hi>Bankers,</hi> as that out of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36377:3"/>any private Pique or Disgust to the persons of them or any of them, he would lay about him as he doth, with a zeal so passionate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable.</p>
            <p>The Design then of this Paper must be somewhat more consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and is of a more Publick Aspect; and consequently the Product of a good Intention to the Common Good of the Kingdom; or its Contrary, <hi>i. e.</hi> the working of an Evil and Mischievous Spirit, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and compass some private End, that cannot be otherwise brought about but by bringing ruine upon the chief Credits of the Kingdom, and discomposure, disorder, and an unaccountable Jealousie upon the minds of the People.</p>
            <p>Of these two so contrary Ends which hath been in this Gentlemans Design, it will not be impossible from the parts of the Letter, well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, and the timing of it, to arrive at a satisfaction in it.</p>
            <p>A good and laudable end I would willingly have found in the drift of this Paper, that however I am satisfied, the effect of what our Author hath done is mischievous, yet I might (as one who knowes that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things we offend all) have retained a favourable esteem of his honest inclinations: But herein I can in no wise reconcile my Reason to any of the Rules of Charity. For it is generally the happiness of a good Purpose to be reduced in all its pursuits to honest Mediums in what it aims at; and it is in truth a Contradiction to the Laws of Property, to do evil that good may come on't. Had our Author design'd sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, he would have looked as well to give some tollerable Proof of what he recriminates the <hi>Bankers</hi> with, as to accuse them; and not only here and there one, but all of them. Nor doth the time of emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Paper, savour less of a Peaceable intention: Was there never a time nor occasion offered these thirty years, before this Gentleman's Son was to come Apprentice, to represent these Errors of the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths (if they have been guilty of them) to the World? For what season then is it calculated? But to follow on the Victory which false Report, wheedling insinuations into the minds of simple and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerate People, hath obtained against the Bankers Credit without cause: When the Minds of Men are so startled by this means, that no man can be trusted though of never so good Estate; and when for this cause, many Merchants and others of considerable Substance, for want of the ordinary supplies of Mony, are like to suffer in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation both here and beyond the Seas; no punctual payments to be made in the course of Trade, as was wont to be; numerous Bills of Exchange returned with Protest for non-payment; Clothiers and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36377:4"/>other Tradesmen forced to keep their Commodities on their hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Merchant can neither get in his own Money, nor raise any upon Credit; consequently Fraughts of our Shipping on a suddain much fallen, and few to be had. One would think the sight of these Calamites should make a wise &amp; good Man defer the prosecution of a thing, never so much unfit in his private judgment, rather then pursue it in the sight of such woful accidents: It hath ever been the principal Wisdom of Discreet and Wife Men, even in the Seat of Government, not to be over hasty in breaking inconvenient Customs once rooted by Time and Use, for fear such Alterations might bring great Disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages upon the People; but to do it by a certain gradation, that the good of the remove might appear through all the accidental Discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of such a change; how much more should our Author in the Point in hand, have considered this Pinciple before he thus laid about him without fear or wit.</p>
            <p>What can this Letter then of our Authors, duly weighed with the Antecedent preparations to it, and its accompanying Circumstances, import less than an inconsiderate and destructive Design to the unhing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all he Credits of the Kingdoms? having its Rise from Anger and Ambition, and in its end aiming at the promotion of Faction.</p>
            <p>The matter of Design being then the Breach of the whole Credit of the Kingdom (wherein the Interest of Trade is most essentially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned) he singles out the <hi>Goldsmiths</hi> or <hi>Bankers</hi> as the chief Seat thereof; and levels two main Pieces of Artillery against them, 1. <hi>Their Crimes,</hi> 2. <hi>Their Insecurity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the first Schedule of their Crimes managed between them and the Merchants in weighing and culling of Money, &amp;c. they being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed chiefly to the <hi>Goldsmiths</hi> of the Old Fashion (as our Author terms them) and not so material to their late and present state, as <hi>Bankers,</hi> I shall leave some of themselves to vndicate, for fear they have no Country Gentlemens Sons put Apprentices to them; only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring him of a few things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That he did very ill, and not like the Man of Conscience to his Country he pretends to be, that knowing of such Practices of the <hi>Goldsmiths,</hi> and that to the term of place where they acted their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice to the Kingdom, he should be silent, when it was in the power of his hand to have discovered and remedied so great a Mischief; no good Laws being wanting on that behalf. Or,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If his confident accusing of them, be more then he hath grounds for, how vile and inhumane is it to reflect at such a rate upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36377:4"/>Men, in a thing wherein not only their honesty is taxed; but their chiefest Interests lie obnoxious to danger. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether he be not unreasonably partial in his reflections; to let the Merchant pass Scot-free, upon such an occasion as that of his dealing for our heaviest Money to transport beyond Sea? For admit the <hi>Goldsmiths</hi> sold it, (which yet must not be taken for granted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause you say so) yet certainly his fault was the greater, who so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustriously laboured to procure such Coyn, with a setled intention of conveying it out of the Kingdom for his private advantage, and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally did so, as you accuse him.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will recollect your self, and think fit to write a Letter against the Profession of a Merchant too (excepting some of your own fashion) and when you have got him under the Foot of your Pride and Folly, as you hope shortly to have all the <hi>Bankers;</hi> we shall be brought into a fine World indeed. Nor so I ought to the contrary, but that they may well desend themselves in what you make the matter of their condemnation; more especially, in that of being Instruments of raising the value of our old Gold. Pray Sir, What made the <hi>Merchants</hi> so forward to Transport it, but that Profit was to be made of it beyond the Sea? and if so, what likelier way to keep it at home, than by advancing its Price here. And if it was sent away when the Rate was raised, would it not much more have been so, if the value had continued less? only perhaps it might have asked a little longer time, by the <hi>Merchants</hi> being put to imploy Instruments somewhat more improper then the <hi>Goldsmith,</hi> to buy it up from private hands. The like may be said for the inequality of the Rate of <hi>Guynnies</hi> (about which the <hi>Goldsmiths</hi> are also accused) which were never by any <hi>Proclamation</hi> of His <hi>Majesties,</hi> declared a Current Coyn of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and limited to a certain Rate; but left under the Notion of a Commodity, to rise or fall in price as the course of <hi>Exchange</hi> went in Forreign Parts; for this very reason, that by such raising of the Rate of them, they might be preserved in the Kingdom, when happily the state of <hi>Exchange</hi> might otherwise have laid a <hi>temptation</hi> before many for their private gains, to have sent them away. Thus our Author may also in other Points have been a very Incompetent Censor of what the <hi>Bankers</hi> have done in this distinct Trade and Mystery. In which Case I have sometimes known a wise Man to have confest divers things to be reasonable and good, when the Nature, Grounds, and Ends of them have been opened by one well versed and experienced therein, that he could not in his own single consideration reconcile the Notion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36377:5"/>of common good and advantage. And if our Author have any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Ingenuity, peradventure he also may reflect upon this his hasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of accusing Men in such matters that he so little understands. It's pretty too to take notice what a young Sophister our Grave Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is become, when he tells us of <hi>seven millions coyned at a time in half Crowns,</hi> which he saith was <hi>apparently reduced to less then one Million,</hi> and layes the whole blame of it at the <hi>Bankers</hi> doors. Seven Millions of what, in half Crowns? he afterwards tells us <hi>seven Millions of Silver,</hi> which our ordinary English Dialect would presently inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret to mean Pounds Sterling, if our Reason (which he never design'd his Letter to be examined by) did not contradict the possibility of the thing, and then the Peoples mouthes might be opened indeed against the <hi>Banker,</hi> which is all the Mark he aims at. But admitting our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to be a little out of the way of writing agreeable English, and that by the <hi>seven Millions in half Crowns, and the seven Millions of Silver;</hi> he intends no more then seven Millions of half Crown pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Lets consider whether he be any more honest in the thing, then he is clear in the expression. Seven Millions in half Crowns, by my Arithmetick, amounts to eight hundred seventy five thousand pounds Sterling that he alledges was then Coyned: But Sir, I have met with as likely an Observer in this Point, as your self, who assures me, it will be no injury to tell you, that you are out in your Calculation almost half in half; and if you be so ignorant, or insincere in an Extream on that hand, how shall we trust the truth of your Observation and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor in what you affirm on the other, that the Money then coyned was apparently reduced to less then one Million by a new mischeivous trade of the Goldsmiths. But I do not well so much as to name truth and sincerity with respect to any thing in this Letter, which was never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed to be drawn up by the line of any such Vettues, Blackning of Men being a far better way to do our Authors business: And it were endless to open all the false suggestions that are in the composition of it.</p>
            <p>Next to that, I find the chief crime objected against them, is, <hi>The great advantages they have made in the course of their Trade, especially when they dealt with his Majesty, and bought up Bills, Orders, Tallyes,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed Sir you do not well to tax them at this time a Day with those Offences. Why did not such an Observer of the State of the Bankers as you, urge their Sin of 10. <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> upon them then? when if your Arguments had been powerful to touch their Consciences, they might by this time have reckoned that Charity in you, which as matters stand,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36377:5"/>they can receive under no other Notion but that of reproach and spite. And yet, hark you Sir Hath it not been the Principle of one you know <hi>That as the occasion and Circumstances may be, there is really no wrong put upon a mans Conscience, nor injustice offered to another, to accept of above</hi> 6 per Cent. <hi>for the advance of Money, nay nor any breach of the Law therein?</hi> And if neither the person of another be oppressed, nor the Law violated, where is the Offence? But now you cry out aloud against the <hi>Banker,</hi> as an unpardonable Extortioner, if in any case he exceed the terms of 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> which renders it not unneedful (for the Readers sake) to put one or two Cases to your enquiry about this matter.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>first</hi> be that of Discounts upon Bills of Exchange, which you tax, among other things as against Law, and very oppressive: But, Why so? Really you puzzle my wits to find a Reason for what you say, and you have given us none to think off. A Bill of Exchange during its Negotiation hath never in any Time or Memory, gon under any other Notion than (till I can find a better word for't) a meer piece of Merchandize, which if a man will dispose of, he must do it at the Market rate, or (to speak more like a Merchant) at <hi>Price Currant;</hi> for there is a certain variation of the rate of Discounts as the occasions for Money are great or less; and they were never higher than your Self and your Con-sociates have lately made them by your new-fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Artifices.</p>
            <p>Another Case lies in the Bonds given by the Merchants to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty at the Custom-house, for the additional Duty upon Wine, wherein the Act of Parl. allows the discount of 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> to the Merchant if he pay ready money. What then if the <hi>Bankers</hi> shall lay down the value to the King upon those Bonds: I put it by way of Inquiry, since plainly that allowance was given, to accomodate the Kings present service, Whether it be an Evil in the <hi>Banker,</hi> to take that allowance, upon serving the Publick occasions with a present supply, on the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of those Bonds, which the Merchant should and might have had by the grant of the Law, if he had paid down the Money himself?</p>
            <p>But what the monied Men and Creditors of the <hi>Bankers</hi> will most look at, is, what our Author will alledge against the Security of Money in their hands, which therefore we must alike look into. And because the Creditor will be nice in his Enquiries here, I will first state his <hi>Objections</hi> truly, and give such Answers as I will with the same free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, leave to the Readers judgment: My design being only to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuse
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36377:6"/>my fellow Citizens and others, that they be not frightned with shadowie appearances, nor suffer themselves to be thus play'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by every fly and subtil Gamster, to disturb the setled course of their lawful advantages, to gratifie the humor of any person or faction, whose end is more themselves than the Publick good.</p>
            <p>He Objects then against the <hi>Bankers</hi> Credit. <hi>First,</hi> There being no safety in dealing with the King, while the deplorable Crys of the Widows and Fatherless are such,
<note place="margin">☞</note> whose Money, as he phrazeth it, <hi>they say at least, they lent his Majesty, and cannot repay them.</hi> And did they not lend it the King? (Why delight you thus in the foul course of casting Dirt?) And for that, Tallyes, Orders, and the Great Seal it self are found to be no security.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That <hi>He cannot imagine how Bread should be got by their Trade of borrowing money at lawful Interest, to lend it upon unlawful to private persons; though they can silence their Consciences forgetting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That <hi>the Bankers are not Men of greater Abilities nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Parts than other Tradsmen, nor better instructed than others to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy greater Stocks in an advantagious Trade,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To these <hi>Objections</hi> respectively, a few words.</head>
               <p>To the first; I take it for granted that the Reasons urged upon account of the detainer of money in the Exchequer, and the stop of the proper Course thereof, did and may give a just hesitation to the minds of men; and his Majesty himself, as well as the People, hath, I doubt not, reflected upon that Counsel, with the greatest dislike and indignation before this day. Our Author nevertheless deals herein very uncharitably with his Majesty as well as elsewhere with the <hi>Bankers,</hi> in alledging somethings utterly untrue; for though there was in that unwarrantable Counsel, a breach upon the Course of Tallies and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; Yet he taxeth the Violation of the Great Seal without ground. He must refer in that point of the Great Seal, to the business of the Custom Farm, in which it is true the Patent that had already past the Seal for the main part of the Customs was resigned up again, but not forced.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Gentleman</hi> I guess cannot but well remember at whose house this was acted, and who had a main hand in the contrivance of it; and if so, he may withal call to mind that the occasion of that surrender of the Seal
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36377:6"/>was from some difference about the Termes of a second Pattent relating to the <hi>Wine Act,</hi> which while the then Farmers insisted upon, and more refused; some of them with less foresight than was convenient, offered the acquitting of the whole Bargain, and the Seal whereby they held their Right in the other Part; and having so offered it, it was accepted as suiting the present Design, without possibility of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman is yet much more out of the way, to assert that the Persons concerned in the <hi>Exchequer Debt,</hi> have not their Interest to buy them Bread: May not a man well doubt the truth of his Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations for so many years past, who errs in a Point that is now in Action; for who knows not that there is a settlement of seventy thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> for two years out of the Publick Revenue under the Great Seal, for the quarterly payment of those Interests to the Bankers? which is so punctually satisfied to all such whose Accounts are stated, that it is not the Kings fault, if every Creditor have not his Interest paid him every quarter day, such Security hath that Great Seal given.</p>
               <p>He knew well enough also, what fresh Assurances are lately made to the Bankers, of having the said Interest continued by force of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Great Seal, and the Additional Hopes (as is most just) of some further way of Settlement for the securing of those Debts: And it is much to be desired that his Majesty will, as from the Honour and Justice of the thing it self, so also from the Consideration of the Industrious improvement of that pernicious Counsel, to him and his Affairs; give some speedy issue to this matter.</p>
               <p>It is to be hoped that such a conjuncture of Affairs, and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our then chief Ministers, as happened at that unhappy jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of shutting up of the Exchequer, will never meet again: Or, that God in his Mercy will give the King, in the experience of the fatal Consequences thereof, a Noble Resolution to discountenance and withstand such ill advice.</p>
               <p>To the second Objection, <hi>That there is no way for the Bankers to get Bread, if their Loans to his Majesty cease;</hi> and for which he gives us this Potent Argument, <hi>That he cannot imagine how they should.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer, That running upon Imaginations as he doth throughout his whole <hi>Letter,</hi> if this prove otherwise, the most part of what he hath said, may be suspected for a mear piece of fancy. He cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it, how? by borrowing Money at lawful Interest, and lending
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36377:7"/>it to private persons at unlawful. No, Methinks it is plain and easie to be unagined, how Money may be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in this way, if they do (as he faith) silence Conscience, forget Christianity, and by Hook, and by Crook, make the most of their Cash by oppressive Exactions: Is it not a wonder his Imagination should fall so short, that is so much in the exercise of it?</p>
               <p>But to disprove our Authors Imagination, without these crooked ways of oppression; ARe there not those among them, who (thanks be to God) have got their Bread, and it is to be hoped, enabled to lay up something for their Wives and Children, without any hazardous deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with the King, or being so exacting as he speaks of; Hath not many been greatly intrusted and imployed this way, since the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer was shut up, who are both able to pay their Creditors, and have got their Bread and somewhat more, and yet stand free from this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by all, but this Gentleman, that its likely never suffered by any of them. Methinks the state of some of them that have fallen by the deadly breath of such as our Author, and have thereby their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in Estate exposed to all, may better instruct him in this Point; and if he had that Christianity in him, which he so much blames o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for, it might and should work pitty and remorse in his Soul, that by his fly Insinuations, false Suggestions, and all manner of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, he should have been a means to bring disreputation upon the Persons, and prejudice upon the Families of such who are by this means cast down.</p>
               <p>It may, and I trust will also teach those that have Moneyes in the hands of such men, not to suffer themselves to be abused by such pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Artifices, while they have hereby been made the Instruments of others undoing, and of injury to themselves, upon the meer Grounds of ungrounded Jealousy: For where is the Person that hath been so earnest upon them for Money; who can define any true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why he hath so done? Only his imagination hath been dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, and his fears raised by the false Suggestions of these pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Incendiaries.</p>
               <p>And what have they advantaged themselves by those indeliberate and forward Demands, but the contrary; for if they had judged of these Artifices as they are, and not run so unreasonably upon those Bankers, they might as occasion required have been sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed as aforetime, with those Summs which they are now forced to stay for, notwithstanding all emergencies, a much longer season.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36377:7"/>
               <p> The third Objection consists of so many Particulars, that I must take them up as I go. He first taxeth them for, <hi>being Men of no greater Natural Abilities and acquired Parts, than other Tradsmen:</hi> What then, Sir? If they have but a proportion of understanding in their Trade, to their Fellow Citizens (for the Trading-Citizens are no Fools) and an honest Design and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in their undertaking it, is enough to their Creditors. I, <hi>But they are no better Instructed than others, to employ great stocks;</hi> Are they not? Then indeed I should think you in the right on't, when you tell your Country-Gentlemen, <hi>That all the Arts a Goldsmith can teach him, will not be worth one of those two hundred Pounds, he desgned with him.</hi> But, pray Sir, where were your Natural Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Acquired Parts, when you thus Wrote? Is there no difference in Skill of this Nature, between a Man whose Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Education hath layn for many years in Credit, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Money, in ways of Advantage, who is known of all that have occasion of Supply for their present Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, to be Persons dealing in that Way through all the various Courses of it, and another Tradesman whose Education and Life, hath only Experienced him in the Management of some particular Commodities, and the Improvement of them to his best Interest.</p>
               <p>Sure, Sir, If you had consulted your self, your Acquired Parts would have told you, there is here some difference; but it bears the shaddow of an Argument against the <hi>Bankers</hi> to the unheedy, and then, whether Sense or Nonsense, Reason or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, Truth or Falshood, all's one with you. But, <hi>They have no greater Skill in Law than others, to judg of Securities to be taken for Money, nor have they more knowledg of Men, to Guess at the Value of their Bonds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How our Authors Passion blinds his Reason! Would you have every <hi>Banker</hi> become a Lawyer, or else leave his Trade? On com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Occasions every Mans Natural Abilities and Experience in the World (whereof I hope you will grant our <hi>Bankers</hi> to have some) may serve the turn; and in cases difficult and out of the way of ordinary Dealings, they are generally Men of more Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their own Estates, and the Trust they have from others, than that I believe they would be satisfied with so much Law as our Author himself hath, when so many able and knowing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36377:8"/>Lawyers are so near at hand. Besides, such a Man of Wit as you, might have considered, that there is a Power in these ways of Credit, to oblige such Men as the <hi>Bankers</hi> deal with, to much Punctuality; and but that I would fain resemble our Author in speaking once like a Man of Mysterie, I could give good Reasons for it: He is miserably out, and speaks as unlike a Merchant as ever I heard, to tell us, the <hi>Bankers</hi> knew the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Men no better than others, when of all in the World they have the Advantage this way. What gives the Knowledg of Men as Men, but Converse? What of the Estates of Men, more than frequent and ordinary Dealings with them in the point of Money? Which with other Collateral Observations that are Coincident with it, gives the truest measure of Mens Estates. How then in these ways, is the Integrity and Generosity of a Mans Dealings better discovered? This manner of Corespon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence then, these Bankers having had with the most they deal with for many years, How should they but know Men better than others, and be able to proportion their demand of Security for them? But our Author is not yet at an end of this Argumentative Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph against the Bankers Credit: I wish his next Reasons be better than his former, and savour more of Natural Ability, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of Mind.</p>
               <p>He puts the Question very seriously from the Premises that I have already Answered, <hi>How then should they be able to make more Interest of Moneys, than other Men?</hi> How then? It's a Deduction from your Premises, is it? Why then Il'e tell you how the Case stands, if some of your Premises have no Reason in them, and others no Truth; what then becomes of your <hi>Hero</hi> then, and of all your Subsequent Arguments, or rather Artificers deduced from them. If they be really more able than other Men to improve Money; if they have as much Skill in the Law as they have ordinarily need for, and know where to go for the rest when Occasion calls, that their Security may be good; If they have more knowledg of Men than others, which are all the Principles that you derive this <hi>how then</hi> from; Why then, I may naturally turn the Argument upon you, and tell you that all your Natural Abilitys and Acquired Parts, have missed the Mark hugely, when you doubt the Bankers Trade to such a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as to make it a Wonder how they should be able to Improve
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36377:8"/>Money better and more securely than others. And if you would know further how they can keep open their Shops, notwithstanding their dead Stocks of Cash to answer ordinary Demands (for such extraordinary and unreasonable Demands, as your Whispering and Calumniating Gang hath lately put People upon, nothing can be Sued for) and Maintain their Servants, and pay their Landlords; I tell you again, that besides the Keepers of their Running Cash, for which they pay no Interest, the Matter lies in their Knowledg and Way of Improving Money, better than others. It's not to say what a Bankers Skill in this sense will honestly extend to: Il'e tell you they are archer Men in their Trade than you and I think of. And I am verily of Opinion, that they make (as you say they must do to get ought by it) more than Nine pound <hi>per centum</hi> of their Money, in their way of Improvement; yet I will not as you do, Charge them with Extortion therein, unless I knew things better.</p>
               <p>You may remember, I have put you two Cases, wherein pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly Ten Pound <hi>per centum</hi> may be got without a Mans becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Transgressor; and the Bankers, it's likely, may know more. We are commanded to have over all, Charity; a Garment that I desire to value and keep uppermost, though you seem so daring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reject it, and to put on that of Censure and Reproach. And truly, every ones Charity is there called for, while we hear no Body crying out against them: None can be Advocate for all of a Trade, but for most of them; the chief Dealers at their Shops cannot exclaim of their Extortion, but that their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and emergent Occasions, have well born the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Requitals, which have been given to them: But certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all will have cause ere long, if the Gentleman gain his end, to cry out upon him.</p>
               <p>The Merchant when it may be, that Two, Three, Four, or Five Hundred Pounds, which might have been had at a Bankers Shop, to serve the Exigency of his Occasions, cannot now be had in the City of <hi>London,</hi> in any reasonable time; or if he may be Accommodated by a Scrivener, the Trouble about it, Procurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for it, and the Time he must be obliged to keep it, beyond the Circumstances of his Occasion, may probably amount to more than Twelve Pound <hi>per centum,</hi> when he might have it at the Bankers at a lesser Rate. The Moneyed Man, when he sees
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36377:9"/>the <hi>Banker</hi> born down without cause, and his own money lying in a Chest without improvement; himself in no way to put it out with security and profit: All that have experienced the ease, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, and prosperous Trade of the City, by and under this way of Credit, and if after all, his own Conscience cry out of him, it is but that which is to be looked for, as the offect of these pernitious and ruinous Contrivances, unless it be already seared as with a hot Iron.</p>
               <p>He would put the Creditors in dreadfull doubt of the <hi>Bankers,</hi> for fear of Informers against them for notorious Contracts, and the pretence of great Charges they are at to keep off Suits of that nature, and to sue out Pardons. And though I have little reason to believe any thing he saith, yet I should have past it in silence were it not for two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First.</hi> That I am confident he never heard of any Usurious Contracts pleaded against them, though they must have been as publick at <hi>Westminster-Hall,</hi> or the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I cannot imagine how our Author should come to know what Charges they are at to keep off Suits of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If he search into the matter, I am of Opinion hee'l find it quite otherwise. And for Pardons, there's an Intimate of yours, that may vye in that Point with any half dozen of the guiltiest of them if I be rightly informed.</p>
               <p>But after all these fine knacks of Conceipt (aiming at reason but unhappily falling short of it) to blast the Credit of the <hi>Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> he darts one more with the same purpose, and tinctur'd with somwhat more than ordinary Anger, That I cannot for my Life discern the Point of.</p>
               <p>It's <hi>Their being trusted ten times more than they are worth upon Personal Security and many times their N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te alone taken for five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds a thousand pounds, or more. And yet those free Lenders, as he calls them, (for he's very much out of Humour) would scarce be satisfied with two or three mens Bonds for a thousand pounds, that are known to be worth, at least five thousand pounds a man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall I ask our Author whether this was practized without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and good experience by those that did it? Surely not without ground, while he characterizeth them to be men so wary in the disposal of their money to others. They knew then what they did; and no doubt acted upon some principles of reason herein,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36377:9"/>notwithstanding your censure of their discretion, from the meer Authority of an, <hi>I say,</hi> for that's the most powerful part of the Argument he uses against this practise, while his pretences of the hazard of the <hi>Bankers</hi> disposal of money, and their capacity to do it more than other men, have already been found so lame &amp; ridiculous. Such an Observer as he, a man would think, might have taken up some considerations from so remarkable and continued a practise as this to have better bethought himself what he was about to do, when he began to breath out such Venom against the <hi>Bankers.</hi> Is't not obvious that the very All of a <hi>Banker</hi> lies upon his utmost pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuality, whereas other men as the exigency of occasions may be, oft times dispence with it without any suspition. Me thinks the very awe of the power of Credits continued through the course of so many years, the free, generous, and unconcern'd reliance of Men upon them; their efficacy to raise, enliven and encrease the Trade of the Kingdom to such a notable degree, should have dampt his confidence in a pursuit of this nature, and forbad his falling foule upon so sacred a thing.</p>
               <p>But the Rise of this design is such as all things must give way to. Here's Anger and Ambition, as I tould you, in the minds of some body, and a New-faction to be introduc'd. And what are the Credits of the Kingdom, the Ruines of the <hi>Bankers,</hi> Disreputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Merchant, Abuse put upon the jealousie of Creditors, Losses of the People, laying wast our Trade, Confusions and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders in the course of all affairs in the Nation. What is their own Consciences, Honour, or any thing, to the wreaking of this Anger, gratifying this Ambition, and pulling down of others that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves may be advanc'd. To arrive at this false accusing and whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering about, from one place of Concourse to another, <hi>How is it with such a Man? Does he pay well, or's at a stand? I hope you are not concern'd. I assure you such a friend of mine hath drawn his money. I wish all be well. A word's enough to the wise.</hi> Some ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the confidence to abuse the Name of a Noble Person, because hee's accounted a wise Man and a fit Example, reporting in the City, and writing into the Country, that his Lordship hath had great sums of money in the hands of such and such which he hath called out, whereas the parties so mentioned ner'e ow'd his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship one farthing: And a thousand such petty (but as they have prov'd over-prevalent) insinuations have been used; vented by their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36377:10"/>half-witted Emissaries, (of which they have both young and old, rich and poor to make use of, and to act their tricks with a world of zeal and gravity) while among themselves they make the best sport imaginable, in telling what a good Instrument (they mean a fool) they have made of such and such a sober Citizen or Inns of Court Gentleman. I say to arrive at these ends of their own, none of these Machinations must be accounted a Crime. And let not our Author tax me of uncharitableness herein, or come with any such disguises, as a Letter to a Country Gentleman hereafter, For upon better Evidence than that the Coyn was carried into the Cocklosts, this is the very Rise and design of this Epistle.</p>
               <p>And what are these Gentlemen that all these things must make way for? Is it not Character enough to tell the Reader, that they are even of the same Spirit with our Author. What need we say more, or what more can be said to shew us what we are to expect from them, when they have made us the silly Instruments of their own Grandeur.</p>
               <p>Can we hope for that good from them they pretend to? Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from those publick Evils and Calamities they complain of? Honour and a Generous Design for the Publick is adequate and like it self in all its Parts and motions. Noble ends are never aimed at by such peaking, base, sneaking and destructive Courses.</p>
               <p>Whither will they have brought us, if they accomplish their ends and gain the Ascendant? Will their Advancement be a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for what we suffer by their means? I doubt, had they a Will to do good, they'l find it hath been an easier business to destroy the Trade and Credit of a Nation, than to heal it, and bind up it's Breaches. As the less difficult part of the two, it will be well if they make not use of our Poverty to oppress, and our Ruine, (much wrought about by our own hands, while we are so fondly influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by their Subtilties) to run us still into further Calamities. For if they have decry'd Credit that the present Incumbents may fall, What will they do in their Places without it? And, if Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney must be had, and no Credit be continued, what way they will advise to, I leave to other Conjectures than my own.</p>
               <p>My Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> tells us, <hi>Nothing doth more hurt in a State, then when Cunning Men pass for Wise;</hi> and yet if all will avail to make the People (whose good I charitably aim at in these Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36377:10"/>to consider what they are doing, while they dance after the Pipe of such Crafts masters as these, and be no more entangled and bercaved of their Wits and Interests by their deceitfull pretences and practises but proceed in all their Concern ments, like men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with Reason, I shall gain my desire. I dispair not of it, though its sad to see the generality so much enclined to another Spirit.</p>
               <p>Our Author ends with a solemn Enquiry, <hi>Whether any Man that hath Exercised the Mystery of Banking, hath living or dying gone off the Stage with a clear good Estate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I had scarce taken notice of it, but that he hath just before been telling us of <hi>Scripture Commands,</hi> and follows it with a profession that he <hi>Judges no Man.</hi> If you know none such that have been acquainted with their Mystery so long, let me tell you, You have either a very short Memory, or have been a very shallow Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But your meaning in this Enquiry is also very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood. And yet it follows; <hi>I Judge no Man.</hi> No Sir, Why rais'd you the question then? If you speak the truth, I doubt you can give no very good account on't. In earnest, I hear of several that are gone off with very clear and good Estates, but I think it not Manners to expose their Names to our Authors Curiosity. <hi>Judg no man?</hi> and yet after the rate you have done, condemn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive their Ruine!</p>
               <p>Give me leave to end with an Enquiry too,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What shall be given unto thee?</hi> Or, <hi>What shall be done unto thee, thou <hi>False Tongue?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>